Victor Manuel Sarmiento Garcia

ECONOMIST · RESEARCH ASSISTANT

■ vmsarmiento@icesi.edu.co | ★ victors081.netlify.app/ | Image linkedin.com/in/victors081

Summary_

Economist and final year student of the Master's Degree in Economics at the Icesi University. I'm interested in working in areas related to applied econometrics, macroeconomics and Statistics. I has experience in the use of technologies that motivate the study of reality from economic theory and that allow processes to be automated while improvement proposals are made. With skills in oral and written communication, achievement orientation, working under pressure, interpersonal relationships, teamwork and leadership.

Education_

Universidad Icesi Cali, CO

Msc, Economics

2023 - Forthcoming

• Courses: Quantitative and Computational Methods, Microeconomics and Market Dynamics, Advanced Macroeconomics, Game Theory and Asymmetric Information, Advanced Microeconomics, Advanced Econometrics I, Advanced Econometrics II, Behavioral economics, Time series, and Analytics models for classification, clustering, anomaly detection, and basket analysis

Universidad Icesi Cali, CO

Bsc. Economics and International Business

2018 - 2022

- · Honours degree: Magna Cum Laude
- · Research assistant and Teaching assistant in courses like: Macroeconomics I, Econometrics I and International Economics

Institución Educativa Liceo Departamental

Cali. CO

High School 2013 - 2017

- Honours degree
- · Talented Mathematics Student

Work Experience _____

Cienfi - Centro de Investigación en Economia y Finanzas

Cali. CO

Research assistant

Feb 2023 - Present

- Program, coordinate and execute Business analytics solutions for companies seeking to answer business questions.
- Investigate different forms of application of knowledge and/or information needs to deepen, expand and complement the development of research projects.
- Prepare research papers, reports and presentations; organize databases; perform econometric and statistical analysis; prepare literature reviews; make presentations to different audiences; edit books; etc
- Prepare learning resources to teach people how to use R
- Technical skills: R, Python, Git, PowerBI, VBA, Suite Office.
- Soft skills: Teamwork, Time management. Achievement orientation, Storytelling.

POLIS - Observatorio de Politicas Publicas

Cali. CO

Research assistant

Feb 2022 - Jan 2023

- I reduced by 50% the time in which a database that captures information about a population survey carried out in Cali was created and cleaned (this involves standardizing, automating and structuring in an effective and efficient way the processes of collection, entry, cleaning, data analysis and visualization).
- I designed a visualization system capable of showing this information in a simple, agile way and aimed at describing the Cali population.
- I centralized these processes in a new area within Polis: Analysis and Methods Management.
- Technical skills: R, Stata, Arcgis Pro, PowerBI, VBA, Suite Office.
- Soft skills: Teamwork, Time management, Storytelling.

Teaching Experience

R basics Cali, CO

Teaching assistant for Icesi's Undergraduates and Pacifico Task Force students

2023-2024

Macroeconomics I, Econometrics I, International Economics

Cali, CO

Teaching assistant for Icesi's Undergraduates students

2021-2022

Publications

FEBRUARY 11, 2024

Determinantes de la aspiración al crecimiento del negocio de los emprendedores Colombianos: el rol de algunas generaciones, Baby Boomers, Generación X y Millenials

Carlos G. Gonzales, Victor M. Sarmiento, Jhonnier M. Arboleda

Revista de Métodos Cuantitativos para la Economia y la Empresa (2023). 2023

Books

Empleando APIs en R: herramientas para el análisis económico

Julio C. Alonso, Victor M. Sarmiento

Editorial Icesi (Forthcoming). Forthcoming

Books chapters

Retorno de la ocupación a los niveles de la prepandemia

Julio C. Alonso, Victor M. Sarmiento

Actualización del sistema de cuentas económicas distritales de Santiago de Cali: 2015-2022, 2023, Cali, Colombia

Working Papers

Ajuste de la ocupación al nivel prepandemia en cinco ciudades de Colombia

Julio C. Alonso, Victor M. Sarmiento

Working paper (Forthcoming). Forthcoming

Comportamiento del índice de precios de servicios energéticos en algunas ciudades del Valle del Cauca, Colombia

Julio C. Alonso, Victor M. Sarmiento, Oscar A. Castaño

Working paper (Forthcoming). Forthcoming

Relación entre el gasto en transferencias de la Premier League y el rendimiento de los equipos

Julio C. Alonso, Juan C. Osorio, Victor M. Sarmiento

Working paper (Forthcoming). Forthcoming

¿Existe una relación de largo plazo entre el desarrollo financiero y el crecimiento económico en Colombia?

Julio C. Alonso, Victor M. Sarmiento

Working paper (s.f.). s.f.

Projects

Exploring the use of time series topology tools for economic series applications

Cali, CO

Master's Thesis

2024

Actualización del sistema de cuentas económicas distritales de Santiago de Cali: 2015-2022

Cali, CO

2023

Cienfi - Alcaldia de Santiago de Cali

- The Gross Domestic Product (GDP) was calculated for Santiago de Cali between 2015-2022
- The adjustment in income distribution after the pandemic was analyzed, the return of employment to pre-pandemic levels was explored, and the dynamics of the Cali economy in that period of time were described.

Efecto Walabí: ¿Y si México jugara en la Conmebol?

Cali, CO

Universidad Icesi

- Data on soccer matches between national teams from 1872 to 2022 were analyzed to measure their effectiveness in terms of a V/D ratio
- The performance of the teams that are part of CONMEBOL and CONCACAF was studied.
- The hypothetical case in which Mexico will play in CONMEBOL against the South American teams was analyzed.

Presentations

2023

Foro Diagnóstico Socioeconómico de Santiago de Cali 2023, Actualización del sistema de cuentas

económicas distritales "SCED: una mirada de largo plazo de la economía Distrital 2015-2022"

Cali, CO

Skills_

Computer R, Python, Stata, HTML/CSS, JavaScript, SQL.

Other

Linux, Shell (Bash/Zsh), LTFX(Overleaf/R Markdown), Tableau, Microsoft Office, Firebase, Git.

Soft skills

Time management, Teamwork, Problem solving, Documentation, Storytelling.

FEBRUARY 11, 2024

Languages_

English Upper Intermediate

Spanish Native

GermanElementaryMandarinElementaryPortugueseElementary

Achievements _____

2	2023	Scholarship Studienreisen für Gruppen von ausländischen Studierenden in Deutschland, DAAD	Germany
2		Deutscher Akademischer Austauschdienst	
2	2023	Master's degree Scholarship, Universidad Icesi	Colombia
2	022	Scholarship tuition fees, Universidad Icesi	Colombia
2	022	Competitor, National Economics Academic Competition	Colombia
2	2021	Icesi - Hong Kong short-term virtual exchange program, Economic and Political Developments in China	Colombia
_		and Colombia	
2	2017	Undergraduate Scholarship, Ser Pilo Paga 4.0	Colombia

References_____

Julio César Alonso
Lina Maria Martínez
Carlos Giovanni Gonzales

Director. Cienfi - Universidad Icesi - jcalonso@icesi.edu.co
Director. POLIS - Universidad Icesi - Immartinez@icesi.edu.co
Full profesor. Universidad Icesi - cggonzalez@icesi.edu.co

FEBRUARY 11, 2024 3